<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Steve Tooke - craftsmanship</title>
  <id>http://tooky.co.uk/</id>
  <link href="http://tooky.co.uk/tags/craftsmanship/"/>
  <link href="http://tooky.co.uk/tags/craftsmanship.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2009-12-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <title>The Language of Software Craftsmanship</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://tooky.co.uk/language-of-software-craftsmanship/"/>
    <id>http://tooky.co.uk/language-of-software-craftsmanship/</id>
    <published>2009-12-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-12-18T10:29:53+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Steve Tooke</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/software_craftsmanship/browse_thread/thread/417bec17184ccfc2#"&gt;software craftsmanship list&lt;/a&gt; had a little flurry of activity today. &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jasongorman"&gt;Jason Gorman&lt;/a&gt; posted about &lt;a href="http://www.teamsandtechnology.com/dh/blog/"&gt;David Harvey&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://qconlondon.com/london-2010/presentation/Danger:+Software+Craftsmen+at+Work"&gt;session&lt;/a&gt; at next years &lt;a href="http://qconlondon.com/london-2010/"&gt;QCon London&lt;/a&gt;. The talk - &lt;a href="http://qconlondon.com/london-2010/presentation/Danger:+Software+Craftsmen+at+Work"&gt;Danger: Software Craftsmen at Work&lt;/a&gt; - unsurprisingly caused some discussion on the list!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linked in the thread is an &lt;a href="http://www.teamsandtechnology.com/dh/blog/2009/05/25/software-craftsmanship-can-we-just-get-over-it/"&gt;interesting article&lt;/a&gt; by David that gives a little bit more context to his position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a problem with the language of software craftsmanship. The notion that somehow we’ll solve
our nascent profession’s problems by calling ourselves, or regarding ourselves, as “apprentices”,
“journeymen”, “masters” and so on is more than faintly absurd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;a href="http://tooky.github.com/craftsmanship/eden/2009/11/25/software-craftsmanship.html"&gt;recently joined&lt;/a&gt; the formal apprenticeship scheme at &lt;a href="http://www.edendevelopment.co.uk"&gt;Eden Development&lt;/a&gt;, and I wanted to give some perspective of what being an apprentice means to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using terms like &amp;ldquo;apprentice&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;journeymen&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; probably a bit absurd. But its absurd in a good way. &lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?SystemMetaphor"&gt;Metaphor&lt;/a&gt; is one of the core practices of XP, developing a system metaphor gives a team a shared vision for project. Its not meant to define what the software does, but the language of the metaphor gives the team a way to discuss the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software craftsmanship metaphor gives us shared vision for improving the state of software development. Its not supposed to be new ideas, its just a new way of framing new ideas to give people a common language to use. Calling myself an apprentice allows me to say that I have a lot to learn, that I want to be part of company that is willing to invest in me, if I&amp;rsquo;m willing to invest in myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I sound absurd when I tell people that, then so be it. It certainly starts the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Software Craftsmanship and Eden Development</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://tooky.co.uk/software-craftsmanship/"/>
    <id>http://tooky.co.uk/software-craftsmanship/</id>
    <published>2009-11-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-12-18T10:29:53+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Steve Tooke</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure when I first came across &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_Craftsmanship"&gt;software craftsmanship&lt;/a&gt;, but I know that &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/edentodd"&gt;Dave Hoover&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s early blogs about &lt;a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596518387"&gt;apprenticeship patterns&lt;/a&gt; were some of the posts that made it really start to resonate with me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I read one of Dave&amp;rsquo;s posts - &lt;a href="http://redsquirrel.com/cgi-bin/dave/2005/04/12#a.thread.of.patterns"&gt;A Thread of Patterns&lt;/a&gt; - and I started to recognise some of these patterns in my own experience. This post prompted me to email Dave and tell him a little of my story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading back over those emails today its striking that I had started to look for a mentor. That I felt that there were serious problems with the way the company I worked for approached software, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel I had the experience to fix those problems, and that I needed to move and take the next step in my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one area that your patterns need to touch upon is getting the culture
right. This is an area that I think is making my life more difficult. There
isn&amp;rsquo;t a culture of developing software in this company. Most of the
programming here is about quick and dirty solutions to solve one time problems
for production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was 2005 - it was two more years before I left that company, and the move I made then didn&amp;rsquo;t work out the way I hoped. I learnt alot along the way, but have never really found the culture I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to today - after 5 months at &lt;a href="http://edendevelopment.co.uk/"&gt;Eden Development&lt;/a&gt; I feel that I have finally found a company with a culture that I share. The company itself has been on a bit of a &lt;a href="http://blog.edendevelopment.co.uk/2009/10/13/software-craftsmanship-a-meeting-of-minds/"&gt;voyage of discovery&lt;/a&gt; and growth and I am really excited to be part of its future. Not only did we leave our old office for the first time today, but the company started its new
formal apprenticeship scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pleased to say that I was offered, and have accepted, an Eden Development apprenticeship under the guidance of &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/edentodd"&gt;Todd Anderson&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see how this program develops, and look forward to sharing my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>UK Apprenticeships and Software Development</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://tooky.co.uk/uk-apprenticeships-and-software-development/"/>
    <id>http://tooky.co.uk/uk-apprenticeships-and-software-development/</id>
    <published>2009-09-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-12-18T10:29:53+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Steve Tooke</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/coreyhaines"&gt;Corey Haines&lt;/a&gt; recently blogged about &lt;a href="http://programmingtour.blogspot.com/2009/09/software-development-school-idea.html"&gt;building a software development school&lt;/a&gt; and it got me thinking about UK &lt;a href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/Employers/Whats-it-all-about/What-is-an-Apprenticeship.aspx"&gt;Apprenticeships&lt;/a&gt; and how we could improve the &amp;ldquo;craft&amp;rdquo; here in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UK Apprenticeships (a rebranding of &amp;ldquo;Modern Apprenticeships&amp;rdquo; - also known as &amp;ldquo;Day Release&amp;rdquo;) is essentially a scheme that combines on and off the job training. They cover a large array of careers but all have the same common principle: apprentices spend most of their time (typically 4-days per week) working in a real business under a mentor, and the remaining time at college studying for a recognised qualification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/Employers/Whats-it-all-about/What-is-an-Apprenticeship.aspx"&gt;Apprenticeships website&lt;/a&gt;) an Apprenticeship is not a qualification itself but a framework  containing separately certificated elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Apprenticeship frameworks cover a wide range of &lt;a href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/Types-of-Apprenticeships.aspx"&gt;industries&lt;/a&gt; including an &lt;a href="http://www.apprenticeships.org.uk/Types-of-Apprenticeships/Information-and-Communication-Technology/ICT-Professional.aspx"&gt;ICT Professional apprenticeship&lt;/a&gt; - I wonder what it would take to develop a scheme for software developers which would enable UK development workshops to start taking an active role in developing the next generation of software craftsmen?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
